Thank
you, Marina.
I'll call the regular meeting of the Inland Wetlands Commission to order.
First up is roll call.
And I
see we've got Bill Monroe,
we've got Jan Maske,
Duncan Fife,
and myself.
And that
is all that's present after Ed Smith declined
to attend tonight.
So,
everybody is seated as a regular member at this point.
Next item on the agenda, changes in the order of the agenda.
And I would like to shift items
9A
and nine B
around so that the election of officers is A and the annual report is B,
because there were some things
that I think once we have the election of officers,
hopefully we'll be able to fill in some missing information
on the annual report
and get that done tonight.
And that is all
I had to change. Does anybody else have any changes or additions?
Hearing none,
I'll make a motion to modify
the agenda by shifting items
9A and 9B around.
Any discussion?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote.
Bill?
Aye.
Jan?
Chair Duncan?
Aye.
>> Chair And I vote aye as well. The motion passes four-zero-zero.
Next up is the approval of the minutes from 07/11/2023,
regular meeting minutes.
Does anybody have any comments on the meeting minutes?
And I had none.
I had none.
Bill or Duncan?
No, no corrections.
Nope.
Should be all set. Okay.
>> Then I'll make a motion to approve
the meeting minutes from 07/11/2023
as
presented.
I'll second. Thank you, Jan.
Any other discussion?
Hearing none, we'll call for a vote. Bill?
Aye.
Jan?
Duncan?
Aye.
>> And I vote aye as well.
The
minutes are approved as presented
by a vote of four-zero-zero.
I don't think I see anybody from the public here tonight, so we will pass on Item five, public comment.
Item six, old business, we've got none,
which takes us to Item seven,
the permit application
for William Nolette,
760 East Street.
Agent Wagner, do you have anything new for us on
that particular
application since the last time we met?
>> No, nothing new.
I did go over there and, walked the property with him again, kind of went over the same stuff we talked about,
make sure everybody's on the same page,
check the the dam that he put in place that's still
holding.
But, yeah, other than that,
nothing new. He said he was thinking of phoning in for the meeting. Was gonna try, but apparently he's not here.
Okay.
>> So what is going on with that? So is it
is
it is
it continuing?
Or
What's what's that?
>> Yeah. Well, I mean, I know you'd started, you know, digging the trench and all that. I mean, so
and I know you went to see him.
>> Yeah. Can he continue or not? I well, I I had told him to wait till you guys approve the permit before he
didn't make work. I just had him put the the dam in and restore the flow to the Okay. The stream that was existing and and basically dry out his
his man made brook until you guys
ok'd everything.
>> Okay.
And so if
we approve it, he'll go in and put the slopes
on the ditch that he had and
do all that.
And that's in the application in your narrative.
He's going to execute in accordance with your narrative. Yeah, stabilize everything, seed it, and
then after inspection, it'll
slowly
release the water.
>> Okay.
Should there be
any
conditions of approval other than your standard conditions, Joe?
>> Let's
see, I was thinking,
I mean, we could do
periodic inspections.
I think I put that in the
application description, that I would inspect it before
the water was released from there.
>> That was the only condition that I was thinking we might add to the list. Yeah.
Put it in when he
>> gets rid of the dam. Yeah. I put it in the project description so we didn't have to add it as a condition,
I mean, we could add it in there anyway just to reiterate it if you want. I mean, it wouldn't hurt.
I think that's the only thing because that's the important part is making sure it's stabilized and doesn't cause any more erosion before
the water flows through it.
>> Could we add a condition that
he
creates
the new stream in accordance with your narrative? Because I don't think your narrative was actually part of the application.
>> Yeah, was. Yeah, it was a project description.
Okay. So it'll be in the permit
that it's,
know,
this project description dated 07/03/2023.
That'll be the one referenced in it.
So
basically have to follow that if the permit's granted.
>> Any other commission members have any other comments on things that we might want to add for conditions of approval?
>> I just have a quick question. If, I don't know, it washed
out or something happened,
you know, down the line on an inspection,
does that get brought back in front of the board or is that something that, you know, just you deal with?
It would be
>> something that I could deal with. If it wasn't
if it wasn't addressed, then
we could take a, you know, a new enforcement action or something. Like, say, the the permit wasn't followed and,
you know, was it was unstable and it was causing more erosion, then we could do a separate enforcement action and bring
that that back because the permit wasn't being followed.
But I think if everything,
you know, everything in the permit is followed, it shouldn't shouldn't create a problem. But if it does, yeah, it could be a it would be basically, it'd be a new violation.
Okay.
>> So just so I understand. So if we give him the okay,
he goes and does
whatever he needs to do Mhmm. Without releasing that water.
And then you go out there,
inspect it.
Yeah. And then at that time, if you say,
okay, is there any other
do we get involved again, or is it just from you?
>> No. I mean, you should be
you should be okay. I mean, I could I'll I'll brief you with a report and probably take some pictures and present them to the commission later,
so you can see what the then result of it.
But as far as you needing to come before the commission anymore, no, it shouldn't need I to mean, I'm just new to this, so I'm just trying to understand. I
>> think it's kind of a go no go, Jen. It's either meets the
conditions that Joe spelled out in the project description
or he doesn't release the water until it does. Joe goes And for
>> if there's something that you
think needs to be added, can you can make a motion to add a certain Yeah. No. I mean, that wasn't the case. It was just to understand how it's
gonna get to the end.
>> Joe, I had a question on that
man made pond.
It was my understanding that it's a man made pond, and there's a stream that runs through it. Mhmm. The stream got backed up. The the silt got backed up and was creating a a flooding situation into his yard near his home.
Is that correct? Yeah.
>> Okay. Yeah. It was it's silted up the stream
outlet, and then the stream was basically had
a really shallow channel. So then
the channel would overflow, and then it would spill into his yard. And then
there was a wetland crossing on the drive, the next driveway down, and it would
the water would basically flow downhill before it reached that crossing, and then it would just flood across the driveway instead.
>> I'm just wondering, since it is a man made pond, can he do anything about that? I mean,
is that like a
once it's a once it's a pond, it's always a pond.
Or can he do anything with that? Yeah. Like,
>> you even if you create
a water course, it still kind of falls. Once you create it, it falls under wetlands regulations.
So even if it was a previous owner, or if it was a grab a pit dug upon and it filled up, then they would they would have to go through wetlands commission if later they wanted to fill it in or change it or something.
So just kind of falls under manmade or natural still.
>> Because I was thinking of it, if
that pond is getting all back, I don't know how what the situation is there. But there's got to be other ways to
aerate that pond.
I mean, there's ways that you can get that water moving without it.
You know, and to
keep it moving and maybe it won't clog
up on you.
>> Yeah, I think it just gets a high sediment load from because basically there's a farm
uphill of
the pond. Over the years, I think all the sediment running into the because there's two other ponds that flow
into culverts and then into the next pond and then into a culvert and then into his pond.
And I think they just collect sediment over the years and it kind of ends up in his.
I
>> think, yeah, you weren't here on the last meeting, Bill, but, you know, one of the things that kind of surprised me is how come the pond didn't fill in but the outstream
did?
You would think the pond would fill in first.
Yeah.
>> Well,
I think I think the pond did fill in. Mean, it didn't completely fill in, but it definitely was a lot of fine sediment. And that's when when he
blew his damn out. And then I got the complaints was was all that fine sediment that collected into the pond and then and then he released it down into this
stream.
>> Oh, so he already had water flowing through the new trench.
>> Yeah, that's what Yeah. I got you. When I saw it, that's what was. And then he
you know, we
I asked him to dam it back up, so he did it when I was there.
>> But it does seem that, you know, the end condition here is going to be better, at least for his neighbor who keeps getting flooded out than it was before,
you know we we did what we're doing so.
>> Yeah, it should be. That's all should be better for the pond to place in the outlet
and.
In the stagnant end so.
Should should improve that water quality too.
>> And nothing has to be done with like at the Hirsch farm
that
no changes have to be made there?
>> No,
I mean, some of that falls under there's there's some agricultural
exemptions that he's subject to, so we don't have jurisdiction over a lot of that, but he's not it's it's just like gradual
sultation through the agricultural
use. It'd be hard
for us to
assert jurisdiction over that
with his agricultural exemptions.
That's kind of where Mr. Nolet got into trouble where he was taking advice from the farmer.
He kind of falls under a different set. They're allowed to do quite a bit more than a homeowner.
>> Any other questions or comments? And again, I like having the discussion.
All good stuff. Don't want to shortchange that any.
So if you got questions,
please bring them up.
Okay, hearing none,
I'll make a motion to approve the application
twenty three-seven
of William Nolette
at 760
E Street
with the standard conditions of approval
and adding the additional condition that agent Wagner be present
to inspect
the new channel
before the dam is removed to release water into it?
I'll
second it.
>> Okay. Thank you, Jan.
Any other discussion?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote. Bill?
Aye.
Jan?
Duncan?
>> Aye. Can I vote aye as well? The motion passes four-zero-zero.
Okay.
That is it for new business. We are going to move on to item eight, agent report and enforcement actions.
>> Alright. I had a
couple of
applications come in. I don't remember if I discussed the 196 Lake Road with you, but it was
removal and reconstruction
of
a 50 foot stone retaining wall and a wooden gravel staircase. So the staircases,
it's like wood four by fours, and then there's gravel filled in it.
And that's
not directly on the shore. It's a few feet from the shore, like it kind of wraps, slopes down the hill at the guy's backyard. There's pictures online.
Yeah, slopes down, and then it ends up about three feet from the shore.
So yeah, so that came and then
the other one was
79 Lakeside as a new
septic system repair. So 1,000 gallon concrete tank and a new leaching system.
That was
think it was about 25 feet from the lake. They had some issues with because they had to keep it
a certain distance from the well.
So they had to put it basically, they had one spot they could put it
the area, but it was all
well drained,
so it shouldn't cause shouldn't cause any problem.
And then we have our
notice of violation
at 7 68th Street, which should be resolved with the permit approval.
Then there was another one I'm working on
that's not on the agenda. Was 31 Burnout Brook Road.
When I was looking at another permit, he had applied for
a carport that was actually didn't fall under our jurisdiction.
But I was looking at the aerial photos, I noticed he did a bunch of clearing and put a bunch of asphalt millings down in Bloemer View area. So
I sent him a letter, and he responded right away, applied for a permit, paid for it. So I just visited the site in the rain today
to look it over and
working on that one now. I'll probably put that on next month's agenda to tell you about it. I haven't posted any of the materials for it yet.
And
I also spoke with Ryan Fitch from the tree farm, and they've been the past couple weeks, they've been working on
clearing the brush and limbs that they caught
from that pond that's off Route 6.
Having them leave some of the
big
limbs and trees in the pond rather than drag them up the hill just because it's
I think it would do more damage to the pond.
I'm trying to bring him up, but he's working on going down and dragging stuff up. And he's got a big pile up in the tree farm that he's gonna chip.
I guess he's on vacation right now, so he's gonna work on it when he gets back from vacation.
>> I was kind of hoping he'd get one of those big cranes down there and just lift those
>> Yeah. They need those out of the pond. The distinctive one that you see along the highway. Yeah. Yep.
We all need one of those.
Anything else, Joe?
No, that's it for me, I think.
>> I have one question for you on 409
Lake Road, and that's where they're building a new house over there.
And I remember in his application,
had a
detention pond
that he was
going to have on the property.
Was that the rain garden?
>> The rain garden, yes. Yeah. Yep. And I didn't know
if that was
something he was actually building in there. Whereas I walked by
there, you can see where there's a natural
depression
in
on the
south side of the driveway there. And I didn't know if that's what he was counting as a rain garden or if there's something else
that I haven't seen him actually doing anything to create a rain garden. So I didn't know if
he was taking advantage of the natural conditions there or
I had missed something on
his application.
>> I don't know. I haven't actually have to go visit the property. Haven't been there in a bit. But I think it was further.
I think the rain garden was further in, like a little closer to the house, in that clear area that I had. Okay, yep. I know there's a big clearing on
>> what I think is the north side of the driveway.
Well, anyhow, I hadn't seen any
groundwork done to create a rain garden.
>> Yeah.
I wonder if they're waiting till they've finished landscaping to do that. Because from what I remember from the plan, I think it was a swale, kind of like a swale going up and
they're going to use that to infiltrate the water. It might be just something they're going to do with
topsoil when they're done, but I'll have to look at it.
>> Any other questions for Agent Wagner at this point?
Okay, that completes that.
Marina, going back,
I was looking at the minutes from the previous meeting instead of the agenda.
And so the discussion on the application should have been old business
and not new business.
So,
I got those turned around. I thought from looking at the minutes, it was new business on the application,
but that was from last month's meeting. This month, it is now old business.
So if you put it in the right spot on there, I'd appreciate it. Sure, I will do that. Thank you.
Okay,
moving on to other business.
And we will start out
with the election of officers.
And I will start by, I would nominate
Bill Monroe
to be the Chairman of the Inland Wetlands Water Coors Commission.
And I don't hear Bill
hitting
A comment? Tooth and nail.
>> I was actually going through all that work that George, our wonderful George
Elliott did before he retired.
And the bylaws, the Andover
chairmans,
Andover wetlands and water courses.
Commission's
bylaws
and.
I don't his
he's got a lot of
chairman has a lot of responsibilities
besides.
This what you did here
going through the list.
And.
I I
I don't know how to put this any other way, except that I'm not really plugged in on the
computer world,
if you will. I don't
this is about as much as I do on computers. This is one hour Zoom meeting
once a month.
I don't have any experience on computers. I I don't send out emails. I don't do text messages. I don't do any of that. You'd be surprised that there are people still like me out there in the world. I'm like,
I'm in still in the '19
seventies,
maybe '70. Yeah, '74 when all that started to change. That all came out. I was I just was working so many hours every day in my every
single day that I never actually
I never got plugged
in and I'm still not plugged in. So I would be Okay with sitting doing like an acting chairman
if we needed somebody to come in and just
do it like what you did tonight, Jed.
But it's the other responsibilities that I think I'd be negligent on. Just I wouldn't even be I would have to get all different kinds of computer equipment, which I don't have.
And I just I
don't know if I'm the right pick.
Would that's
>> all I got to say. Wanted to let you know.
>> Well,
the
I so
I'm hearing that you would prefer
not to be the chairman.
>> I would be okay with doing something like, I don't, you know, I realize that even being an acting chairman is like putting a pronoun before the word chairman.
What about putting two pronouns before that? How about like acting
co chairman
and maybe have two chairman for a little while?
And that somebody that can do all the
computer work that needs to be done,
sending out
information
and
to different parties,
and then somebody that can just kinda run the meeting a little bit
or at least,
like, run the meeting until
it gets hung up and then ask you, what am I supposed to do now? Well,
>> you know, one of the things that
could be possible
is
that
I know before
each planning and zoning meeting,
I get together with Jim Hallisey.
And, you know, I get
a lot of training by him, and we do a lot.
I think,
you know, Agent Wagner would be
very amenable to working with you there.
You go back to the bylaws,
and it says we have two officers. We have a chairman
and a vice chairman.
And so
we probably
ought to
go with that. One of the things I was going to talk about a little bit further
on when we
look at the annual report talks about two people did the
state's inland wetlands watercourse training.
I think, I know I was one, and I thought it was very helpful.
And probably,
I don't know if George was the other one or if somebody else had done that or not. But
unfortunately,
my memory isn't very good, so I don't remember a lot of what I got done in training. But I did think it was very worthwhile when I was going through it, And maybe it put a couple of nuggets in there. So that would be something,
and I don't know what your
time schedule is, Bill, to
support that.
I do think it's,
you know, at this point, you know, it's probably not
fair to nominate Duncan.
He's
got, you know,
the smallest amount of time
here.
But if you look at what I did for this meeting and the last one,
all I did was run the meeting, you know, and it
went okay. So, Joe did a pretty good job of
getting all the stuff
ready to go.
And I'm sure that there could be some on the job trainings you go through.
But
I'll just throw another
rock out in the pond
and nominate Jan Maskey to be the chairman.
>> Oh, no.
No, I mean,
we talked
a couple of weeks ago, and
I
said I could help with the computer part of it.
That doesn't scare me.
So if that was the issue,
you know, if if you're going to struggle with the computer, I could help on the computer side and maybe as a team, we could get it done. I mean,
I'm very green. I'm the other one that took that course. There's a lot of information.
It it certainly didn't sink in.
>> Yep.
I know exactly what you mean. Yep. Yep. But
>> I'm willing, you know, I'm willing to to to take on the challenge, not chairman, though, not chairman.
But
I guess I'd be willing to help. Pickings are slim.
>> Yep.
I think that's the situation we're in really, even though I've
been on the commission for
a couple of years now.
It's all been
on
Zoom.
>> And yeah, and you and I talked about that and I said,
why are we still on Zoom?
>> Well, it's I was going to go like it's
isolated,
you know, on a Zoom
thing. It's really not all that helpful for developing,
you know, skills as a commissioner, you know, when you're just learning to be a commissioner. It's it's a real a little bit for me anyway. It's it's it's.
I
don't know. Get I get the I you know, I kind of didn't get the gist of a meeting
and all, but
I think we're missing out on some stuff
that to to improve our skills that we only we have three members now and I consider myself a newcomer even though
I've been doing it for a couple years because it's been all on Zoom all the time.
>> But don't you think I mean we're both on that other committee, I mean don't I get more out of the other committee being
face to face with people.
Is it that January
appeals zoning appeals.
Okay, yeah.
>> Right.
You can, you can have a conversation,
you can have a side conversation with someone and you know, pick up a little bit more than kind of here you got a one at a time thing.
>> Well, think we are still on Zoom meetings because George found it easier to hear.
So
I think, you know, the calendar
for the community room is probably
show to have to check out for us there, but I bet you the
space
in the community room is
available on
our standard meeting nights
because I don't see a lot of other stuff on the town calendar
for them.
So that is something that the chairperson
could change
very quickly.
We
went back to in person meetings with planning and zoning and
actually we're doing it hybrid now and it works pretty well.
We do, the So Commission does meet in the community room and there are a lot of advantages to that.
Would the two of you, and unfortunately,
know, Ed Smith
gives inklings that he might be coming back to full membership and he might be
the most
knowledgeable
on this stuff. I'm not sure if he'd be willing to do it and he chose not to attend tonight, so I can't put him on the spot. I was hoping to twist his arm and put him in some pain there after
he had whatever else replaced, but
it's going to work, you know. If
we were to have Bill as, you know, the chair and Jan as the vice chair,
would that be
acceptable to
make it go? And you're not there alone. Joe's got the obligation to
make sure you guys are ready to come in and succeed. Can I add something too? Yeah. Yeah. I
>> know,
like
when I first started here, Megan Lowley was the chairman,
and she was very hands on. She was
always calling,
talking, emailing me. We're going back and forth a lot. She would draft the agenda, she would do
a lot of emailing.
So
then when George took over, it was basically like I draft the agenda and then check the links, and and then I send it to him
the week before. And they're like, hey. Review this. Let me know if you want me to add or change anything. And he would, you know, add this, delete that, whatever.
It's good.
So it kind of took much more passive role. So I basically
never met with him. Don't think I ever met with him outside of the meeting.
Really?
I mean, it really depends on
what you want to do as a as a chairman, you know, if you wanted to draft the agenda, if you wanted to have a hand say in enforcement actions or,
you know,
a lot of that, you can kind of take a more active role if you wanted to
sit back and, you know, just proof it before it gets posted and
and stuff like that. And, I mean, that's kind of what George was doing. So he basically just ran the meetings and
and he would he did the annual report. But, I mean, that's kinda kinda work off the previous year. And, you know, I had the
stuff and check with it, I'd be willing to help with that too.
Yeah, it's kind of you can kinda customize a little bit to
suit your skills.
I mean, again, running a meeting like a chairman, you don't really need,
you you need to know how to run the meeting efficiently and legally, it's not
necessarily you don't need to have the most
wetlands experience to do it.
It's more of the procedural aspect of it that
that
is good there.
>> I mean, I just my personal I don't wanna be thrown to the wolves. I I you know, like,
sink or swim kind of thing. That's what I'm, I would be nervous about.
Megan is my neighbor.
So, I mean, I could reach out to her and, and, you know, ask her for a little help. But,
and I'm sure she would.
Yeah.
>> You know, that that's my fear is, you know, how much help will
Bill and I get?
>> Yeah. I mean, usually, I mean, if I'm here,
I would
I mean, that's basically I I did a lot of the meeting prep and stuff. And like I said And I gotta tell you, that's another thing with these Zoom meetings. Like, you you say you're here.
>> I I'm sure if you and I walked past each other, you know, we wouldn't know that we were Yeah. You know, and that's what I don't like about the Zoom meetings. I I understand through COVID, you had to do it this way.
>> It would be nice. It would be nice to see people. I'm a fan of in person meetings too. We we went back. I'm on Wyndham's Wellings Commission, and we went back quite a while ago
to and we do a hybrid one, so people can
phone in or log in if they need to, but everybody
is pretty much there.
>> Yep, that
little
owl
camera that Eric's got in the community room seems to do a pretty good job for the hybrid beatings, you know, and Marina knows how to work it. She's a pro.
Nice. And so, it
goes well. So,
I think, you know, it's
an easy transition.
We just have to have Joe check the calendar to make sure the room's available before
go that way.
I don't know, Bill, what do you think?
>> Oh, I'm all for,
even if it's just temporary,
at least until, like, whoever this transitioning
period. If we screw up,
then we're out.
No, no,
that's
so easy.
Easy.
>> Yeah, right. I'm going to stay on the commission one way or the other if I'm chairman or if I'm a just a regular member,
I would rather
I would rather,
you know, through this transition, I would rather see us go to the community room. I think it would be really helpful for, because you we really have three, three little ducklings here. I
still consider myself
a newcomer.
And
I think it would help us a lot.
it would I think it would solve our little dilemma for the moment, and then we'll work from there after
so many meetings if we feel like, Okay, I got this.
If we don't
>> know, Ed, how long has he been on the
this commission,
this group? Who?
>> Ed Smith.
Oh, well, he's been on longer than I have, and I've probably been on,
you know, maybe
three to four years. I can't remember.
Was And you just don't want to be chair?
>> No,
I've got, you know, planning a zoning chair
keeps me
fully engaged
with more hours per week that I should be putting into
to down stuff.
You know, I'm on this commission as the liaison because I find it helpful to hear what's coming down the road so I can get a step ahead of it and figure it out from zoning perspective.
Not something that I'm going to be chairman of the two different commissions.
We've got enough people,
somebody else can be the chairman of this one.
Bill, it's up to you.
>> Well, so I don't know.
Would be I would accept that chairmanship,
but with conditions.
Conditions of approval?
>> Yeah, I'll it's
like
one thing is we we need at least temporarily
to have some live meetings.
So that just
to just even to little things like, you know, when you ask a question,
I was listening to your let's make a motion. Is
there any discussion? It was like, when are these questions exactly? What, you know, what, just the
time that you ask them, and you know, it's like that.
And
I
am totally
no help when it comes to
emails.
I don't do that stuff.
You know it's
>> I that's why I was kind of how many emails did you get from George?
>> Well,
went out emails, I get emails, but I don't send them out. Know I gotcha.
Once in a while I'll hit that little arrow there and then you can type something in and then you can send it back.
That that part.
>> That's about all I really know. And if anything doesn't go perfectly the way it's supposed to go,
you're not going to get any information.
>> Something there's a hiccup, I'm done, know, it's like, okay, no, I
>> understand.
Think,
you know, that's solvable with the help of Jan or Joe.
You know, nobody's nobody's going to hang either. Of you out to dry on that.
There's nothing to be gained by that.
>> Yeah, mean, could work with that. If you wanted a paper
draft agenda to work off of, then
>> I could print it out and we could I print it out and I have to look at
I'm one of these guys. I have to look at that. A No, I
>> I'm not a loaner, Bill. I print out all that stuff to review it. I don't want to review it on the screen. I like to make notes on my paper copy and all that kind of stuff.
>> I also have something
that I remember Megan sent it to me. It was
like a slideshow on how to run legal and effective public meetings, and it goes through a lot of that procedural stuff that you're talking about, Bill.
That one's pretty good. I'll find it. I think I have it on my computer. I can find it and send it to everybody.
It's good information to know.
>> It is good. And sometimes,
you know, I know
I've been known to goof it up every now and then,
but Marina makes it look good in the minutes.
Yeah, you should see us in Wyndham.
Yeah, okay.
>> Maybe we can get some glass out of it if something else. And I do think
>> that
both you and Jan would be surprised how fast you learn when you start doing it.
And Bill, we can make it so that you can do more than just get email. We can teach you how to send one out. I'm
absolutely confident that we can get
the whole
thing set up in your directory.
All you have to do is type
in IWWC
and all the members show up.
It's all set and ready to go out.
>> Yeah.
Okay, well, so where do we go from here? I mean, do you, it sounds like you need to have some kind of an established chairman and established
vice chair.
I
again,
think if we can, our next meeting should be live.
>> Okay,
well, you know, in
and
I'm not computer smart enough where I'm willing to go out and check on the town calendar right this minute to see if there's anything else going on.
I am confident enough to know that we can vote to go back to live meetings.
Joe can check if he's not doing it even as we speak
to see what the calendar's got there and
go live. You know,
we'll take that up as an
item under miscellaneous tonight
that
we're
going to we'll vote on going back to in person meetings.
You know, I don't think
Joe's already at town hall, it's no imposition for him.
>> No one's
in there now. I don't usually see anybody on our meeting tonight.
So tonight, it just says Board of Fire Commissioners,
>> regular meeting, seven to eight. Yep. They do that over. They do that over the firehouse.
Alright.
>> So then there's nothing else on calendar? I think it is open for us. We just choose not to use it.
Like Jed said, I think George was happy doing
the meetings from home.
>> Yeah. And in the winter, we might decide that you have time to go back to doing it from home. Don't know. Absolutely.
Yep. Absolutely.
>> When the weather is nice and it's late, late, you know, reason not
to go over to town hall and benefit
from the in person meeting.
Yeah, that's what it says.
>> Okay,
so anyhow, we've got, I have nominated
Bill
for
chairman.
I haven't heard of any other,
I haven't
heard Bill say, No, I won't do it.
Haven't heard anybody else says, yes, I'd like to be nominated too.
Do you need a second?
I'll second it, Bill.
She's helping you out. Thanks.
Aye.
>> Okay.
So,
there we have the motion.
It's seconded.
And
I'll call for a vote. I'll let you start, Bill. Aye.
Jan?
Aye.
Duncan?
>> And I vote aye as well. Motion passes four-zero-zero
that Bill is the Chairman.
Okay,
next up is vice chairman,
and I nominate Jan Maschke.
I'll second that.
Okay.
>> So, first, do I have to become a member first? Because now I'm an alternate. Alternate.
>> Oh, yes. Member?
Yeah. Yeah, yeah, we did talk about that. Yeah. And
>> So, I go back or can I just forget I was ever an alternate?
>> It was only for a month. Joe, you have any sense on that?
My
thought to Jan was that if we have an opening on the Commission,
we can fill it, and we can fill it with an alternate
from the Commission.
Well, guess if I'm chairman.
I remember joining even on the on the website
>> It's still listed as a regular number, and it's still because it was just when it it was just last month I switched to the alternate.
>> Yeah, and Ed Smith is an alternate. He still
hasn't said that he doesn't want to be an alternate, so there's still.
>> A We've got room for some member vacancy anyway because guards five room for five members.
Yeah. So everybody could be a full member Everybody could be a full member. And and I'm looking forward to having Ed be a full member here after he finishes his recovery.
But as far as I'm concerned,
Jan, if you have no objections, you are now a regular member.
I will make the annual report reflect it as so. That's why I wanted to do the That's why, yep.
After.
Okay.
Any other nominations for vice chairman?
You sure, Duncan?
>> I think maybe once I spend a little more time on the board and understand the flow of everything we'll see how it goes but I'm definitely open to it in the future.
>> Good. Good.
So, can I ask?
Is there a term on this or is it
can it be changed at any time? Are we locked into something?
Let me
Let me ask it to the chairman.
>> I think it's for a year. I think it's in Well,
>> and I was going to so when we talk about the bylaws, we're not there yet,
it does talk about a one year term.
I thought it should be a two year term
just so that, you know, and I also looked in the bylaws for this. Nothing
that I could find in the bylaws
discussed how long
our terms are. But George, you know, said that
we were nominated for two year terms with the Board of Selectmen.
And
I thought chairmanship should maybe run with that. But
right this minute, I think it talks about a one year
tour
in the bylaws.
So if you voted not to change that, you know, that
one year goes by before you can blink an eye.
>> Yeah,
think that's a good thing, especially right now because
you might not want me on there for two years.
>> Okay.
Well,
we'll take that one step at a time. Okay. Sounds good.
A year from now, you'll still be the most experienced guy on the commission.
>> Well, you never know. Some things
change.
Was a little surprised that everything is in
the wetlands is appointed
Or we volunteer and then we're appointed?
There's
no election or anything like that, not like the other committees.
>> Well,
most of the commissions
are appointed.
You know, if you look on the website
at all the different commissions out there, there's probably 23 or so.
You know, there's a bunch.
There's
a handful that
get elected Board of Selectmen,
Board of Finance,
Planning and Zoning,
Board of Ed, Zoning Board of Appeals.
I don't know if any of the other ones do or not, but those are the ones
that are elected.
Oh, I see. And
>> all the rest are
appointed by the Board of Selectmen.
Okay.
>> There was a question out there somewhere. Guess the term, it was on the term length and right this minute,
it is in our bylaws is one year.
Okay.
Let's run with that. Okay.
>> So,
I think we're any other discussion on Jan being the vice chair?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote. Bill? Aye.
Jan?
Aye.
>> Duncan?
And I vote aye as well. The motion passes
four-zero-zero.
Congratulations,
Jan. Congratulations,
Bill.
I'll do my best.
>> I know you will. And
it'll go fine because,
as you say,
you know, it's
there's
no advantage
to any of the Commission members to have you not be successful.
That just means one of the rest of us would have to go do it. And I really appreciate
you guys stepping up to
take that on.
Okay.
That completes
the election of officers.
The annual report, now we can talk about that a little bit tonight or we can
put that off and Bill, you'd be able to
take approval of that
as an action at the next meeting.
But
as I read through it, you know,
there weren't a ton of highlights
in there on what went on, but
there are some to be determined and vacants that we can fill in and we can get Jan up in the regular commissioning spot
and
>> straighten up that little membership block.
But other than that, I did not have
much in the way of comments. Now, there's no due date for submitting this, so it's not like we got a time crunch.
We could maybe get
report
tweaked up with the with the membership things and then
vote on it next month, if that's okay with you, Bill.
>> Yeah, I would think so.
That way we can.
Right now I'm running blind. Can't even turn on anything else to to look it up or or whatever. Who
>> right now?
Who who's the author of the annual report? I think George. Yeah.
Yeah. George. George wrote this one.
Okay.
>> I think he just kinda goes off of
goes off of the previous year, and then you change, you know, whatever,
add whatever you want. I think there's been
there was more detail on some of the other ones, I think. But it was kind of a slow year last year, and this year is kind of slow too. So
>> Oh, okay.
Good time for some new leadership to take over.
>> Well, was gonna say, so, I mean, I don't have a problem updating this.
Who's got that file?
Well, wasn't it? Didn't Joe send out the file
>> that he sent out? I sent the draft to everybody. Yeah. So, So, that's it. There's nothing else. No.
>> So, if you want to update that in preparation for the next meeting, Jan, that'd be great.
>> Well, was gonna say, does it just need updating with the names? Yes. And that's it?
>> That was all that I saw needed to be done in there.
Okay.
I can do that.
>> And so, yeah, on that second line where it says, Vice Chairman, vacant to be determined, now it says,
All vacant Jan
>> right. Bill, I'm putting you in highlighted.
All right. But everything else, like the application received, all that, that's All that's
>> good to go. Okay. There's no changes.
Unless somebody
has some stuff that
they wanted to add to it, but
I didn't see anything that jumped out at me that we should be adding to it
at this point. Okay.
And then where does this go? Just
>> to Joe? Once we approve it at the next meeting,
I would say that
you will help Bill
forward that to
Kate,
copy to Eric,
you know, so that they can, they build an annual report that's a compilation
of all the different commission reports.
Oh, okay.
But
we have to approve it first.
Yep.
Okay.
>> And I don't know that we have to approve it, but that's what I do. You know, I think that's
you
want to have it be
the consensus of the Commission that Okay. So, mean, I
>> fix it, whatever, update it, and then we attach it to the meeting, to the
agenda going out for next month? Yep. Okay.
All right.
>> Okay.
So, that completes our discussion on
on the annual report.
Next up is the review of the bylaws.
And I don't know if everybody's had a chance to review the bylaws.
Bill, did you see where those are online?
>> Well, I'm
using my wife's
iPad and
George sent the email out like
21 and it's still on here for some reason. And I said, well, that's a great thing. I it's on my iPad. That's how I got it. I don't know how else you get it. Okay,
>> well, so
you have to change the search date, right?
Marina, if you allow me to share my screen, I'll get brave and try and call up the website.
Okay.
Okay. Did it work?
Well, let's see.
Not yet.
>> Well, it
did work,
but it was on the laptop
that I was prepared to
share that and not this.
It's not going to work tonight.
>> Is it just the town website? I have it open here.
Do you want me to pull it up? Yep, that'd be great. Thank you, Marina.
Right.
There.
You'll just have to tell me where to go
when I get here.
>> Okay, so that's the
town of Andover website, Marina. If you click on the government
thing there, now we come down and we'll click on appointed boards and commissions.
And then scroll down until we get
and we were talking about which ones are appointed and which ones are elected. All these are appointed.
And
we clicked on
inland wetlands
there.
And this is the inland wetlands
homepage.
And if you see over on the left hand side in that little green box,
you click on
the bylaws,
that takes you to the bylaws and that calls them up there. So
So, that's how you
get to the bylaws.
So, the bylaws haven't been updated since '21?
>> That's correct. And that's,
you know, essentially two years ago from the last appointment,
you know, and
I didn't,
I don't recall when I looked in there and there's 27 pages, so we won't find it.
Well, maybe when we're coming down to the table of contents here,
we'll see.
Yeah,
I don't think there's anything on there on
updating them. But, you know,
what it says in the planning and zoning is after each election,
chairman can update the
bylaws.
So my assumption was
that
after each appointment,
which we've just gone through, we're all recently appointed by the Board of Selectmen,
That would be a good time to
oh, actually,
scroll down to
Section seven, Marina, under Election of Officers.
Maybe
that's where I saw something on there.
So, yeah,
under the 07/2001,
first meeting July will be the annual organization meeting, which time officers will be elected and bylaws reviewed and made part of the minutes of the meeting.
So,
I don't know.
I would have thought that it would say something about updating the bylaws,
but
we're
reviewing them and
we can update them
as appropriate.
But
that was all that I recalled seeing about the bylaws as I
read through this
earlier.
It does say one year too on there. Yeah, no. And that's why when I was reading that, I said, that should be two years because we should do it after we have a reappointment by the Board of Selectment. But we can certainly keep it, you know, at the one year point at that
point.
So, my recommendation would be that, you know,
the next meeting, everybody take a look at that.
When I reviewed it today,
I had two comments on
the bylaws. And one
is on page 13. So if you scroll down one more page there, Marina,
and it talks about,
I think,
where it talks about holidays
and
it might be in the first paragraph.
Yeah, the fourth line down. If at any time the regular meeting date is a holiday,
the regular meeting will be held on the following Thursday
unless otherwise scheduled in the early calendar.
And since I've been on commission,
we've always met on the Tuesday of the following week.
And so, I would say we should update the
bylaws to reflect
that's our practice.
But other than that, I thought the bylaws were in pretty good shape.
So,
we
already talked about the one year term versus two year term. We want to keep that.
My only comment would be
that we
put in the bylaws that we will, you know, for a holiday, we'll meet on the following Tuesday.
But
I think, you know, we should
review it as we get ready for next meeting,
and then Bill can, you know, act on
any updates
desired to the bylaws. And I don't think there'll be very many. I think they're in pretty good shape.
Sound like a plan, Bill? Yes.
Okay.
You can close that out, Marina. We're
done with the bylaws for tonight. Thank you very much.
Last item is membership and recruitment for the twenty twenty three-twenty twenty five term.
And,
you know, we still do have
some spots available. If anybody's
aware of people that,
you know, would like to do a little volunteer work for the town
and join us,
I think
Ed will
pop up into a regular meeting
as early as next month
so we could use three alternates,
and that's a very easy way
somebody to start participating in the town stuff.
And it's important to the town, so
it's
good stuff there, but I don't have any other leads now. I gave all my leads to George and
I don't think any of those came to fruition at the present.
But if you guys know,
ask if
they want to join, you know, have them show up, watch a meeting or two, and we'll go from there.
>> Good. Can I ask a question? Yep.
On the
annual report, you know where the names were? Going through that.
You need just have the planning and zoning representatives
there
on this agenda or on this?
Do you have your name? It says regular commission plus and then it says planning and zoning?
>> Yep. So
In the bylaws it says that planning and zoning will nominate
a Member to be a regular Commission Member so. Oh okay. So.
That's me.
>> Okay, but so it needs to be there Yep. It needs to be identified. Okay. Thank
you.
>> Okay.
Any other questions on any of those topics?
Okay, next item up is the next regular meeting,
Tuesday, September 12, because of the Labor Day holiday
at 7PM.
And
this is a good time to discuss.
Does anybody have any concerns about
meeting in person over
in the community center?
Certainly.
>> And I guess we've heard from Jan, heard from Bill. Duncan, you're the I
don't know
you can't have to travel more than 15 miles if you live in Andover, so you can't be too far away from the town hall. It's not that town Yeah, we are on all four meetings
>> in person. Okay. Haven't
met everyone yet, so I think that'd be a good thing. Yep,
>> think And it
so
we will do that, Joe.
So
make sure that you go in and
make sure that
the town clerk
has
the meetings
on her calendar
because that's the official calendar.
And as we saw in our last planning and zoning meeting,
I had the only thing listed on the town calendar for the last Tuesday,
but on Carol's calendar, it was something different. She had the Republican
caucus
in there.
And so
we ended up meeting
online last
month for planning and zoning.
So
check out
her calendar and make sure that
she knows
that we're planning on meeting just so there's no hiccups
with that.
>> Okay.
Is this, so would this be a hybrid meeting or would it just be a full in person meeting?
>> I would say hybrid if we need it.
If somebody can't make it, like, say, Ed
I
know I I saw them using that at at the caucus, and
seems like it's pretty
good. I mean, was there except there was a few people that couldn't make it, some handicapped people.
>> The
other advantage to doing the hybrid
is that it makes it easy to record.
I don't know how the Commission's
well,
I'll ask Bill, how does the zoning
Board of Appeals
record their meetings?
I think maybe you should ask Marina.
Okay, I'll ask Marina.
I am the recorder.
>> The
last one
I did a couple of weeks ago was just in person.
No Zoom, no hybrid,
nothing. So I just took the minutes while I was sitting there, took some notes and Yep. It was a pretty short meeting.
Okay.
>> But, Marina, do you know how to do
like, if we did wanna do a hybrid, do you know how to set that up? Oh, shoot. Oh.
>> Yeah. I've I've been doing it for planning and zoning with Jed when they switched to hybrid.
>> So I mean, could you just show us our next meeting or Yeah. Yeah. And I think Eric actually bought a laptop
>> strictly for
hybrid meetings. It's locked to a cart in the community room, so it connects right to the big screen, the big TV that's on the wall there. And then there's the camera
for the hybrid meetings there too. So pretty easy to set up. Yeah.
>> For us that attend,
all we have to do is show up, you know. Right. The
owl camera focuses on who's ever speaking and projects you onto the screen.
So it's really easy from a participant standpoint.
If you wanted to present something, that would be a little different. You'd have to, you know, bring in a laptop or send it to Joe or Marina so that they could, you know, put it up on the screen.
For
us to show up much easier than Zoom.
>> So,
it may be nice. I mean, hopefully we all can attend next, you know, next meeting,
but it'd be nice while we're all there.
If Marina, if you could show us.
Like I said, just in case
Ed can't make it and he wants to dial in or whatever. Right.
Yeah, we can do that. Yep.
>> Okay, so that's the next meeting will be in person hybrid
from the community room
on September 12, 07:00.
Anything
else that anybody's
>> got on their mind here before we adjourn? Chad, I was just looking at the calendar quick
to see if there is anything that night and there is a recreation commission meeting, but I think they normally meet in Carol's office.
So I don't know if Joe, if you're there tomorrow, if you wanna check with Carol and see
Yep. That's it. What your plan is?
>> Yeah. I'll have to look. I'm actually leaving
leaving town tomorrow, but Oh, okay. I'll I'll send her an email tonight. Yeah. Leave here.
>> Just I was gonna say, Joe, I could call tomorrow.
It doesn't matter.
Do you want me to take care of it? You wanna go on vacation?
Yeah.
I mean, I can call her about setting up the meeting, you know, on the calendar and stuff. Okay. All right? Yeah. That'll work. And then I'll just I'll verify that September 12 deal.
Sounds good.
>> Okay.
Got it.
Anything else before we adjourn?
Well, again, thank you, Bill. Thank you, Jan,
for stepping up.
And
we'll make sure that
we succeed there with the help of Joe. And
I make a motion that we adjourn.
Second.
I'll second it.
>> Duncan, did you second that?
Yes, I did. Okay. Duncan. Think Duncan got in there first. So Duncan
was the second.
All in favor say aye.
Aye.
>> Any opposed?
Any abstentions?
Motion passes four-zero-zero.
Thank you very much everybody for attending tonight. We'll see you in person
next month.
Good night, everyone. Good night, everybody.
Good night. Bye.